Erik J. Peterson

CONTACT Information

E-mail: erik.exists@gmail.com Webpage: http://robotpuggle.com

Interests

I'm a neuroscientist with machine learning expertise. I've worked in both industry and academia. I have studied curiosity, play, and open-endedness in reinforcement learning. I've studied coordination in biophysical and artificial models. I am presently focused on designing new systems for automated causal reasoning in complex systems.

Positions

Pastuer Labs - New York, NY

Senior Research Scientist

2022 - Present

I am a technical lead building systems for automated causal reasoning on complex, multi-part, problems in physical science.

Carnegie Mellon University - Pittsburgh, PA

Research Fellow (Research Scientist)

2018 - Present

Curiosity learning. Reinforcement learning. Astrocyte computation. Deep neural networks. Game theory.

Kernel, LLC - Los Angeles, CA

Senior Research Scientist

2017 - 2018

Technical lead building a *real-time* system for complex spatio-temporal field shaping in deep-brain stimulation. Biophysical modelling. Deep neural networks.

U.C. San Diego - San Diego, CA

 $Postdoctoral\ Fellow$

2014 - 2017

Novel theoretical accounts of neural oscillations. Biophysical modelling. Information and compression theory. Advised and developed machine-learning tools to analyze electrophysiological time-series data. Software development.

University of Pittsburgh - Pittsburgh, PA

 $Postdoctoral\ Fellow$

2012 - 2013

Theoretical and empirical analysis of human decision making. Machine learning analysis of fMRI data. Software development.

Colorado State University - Fort Collins, CO

Graduate Research Assistant

2006 - 2012

Human reinforcement learning. Category learning. Modelling, and fMRI data analysis. Software development.

Biosearch Technologies - Novato, CA

Research Assistant II

2004 - 2006

Optimization of high-throughput chemistry. Reporter gene development.

Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory - Livermore, CA

Research Assistant

2003 - 2004

Self-assembly of virus particles to build functional nanostructures. Mechanisms of "ink" transfer in Dip Pen Nano-lithography.

EDUCATION

Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO

Ph.D, Psychology 2012

M.S., Psychology 2009

California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo, CA

B.S., Chemistry and Biochemistry; Minor, Philosophy

May 2004

PUBLICATIONS

- Lavin A, Zenil H, Paige B, Krakauez D, Gottschlich J, Mattson T, Anandkumar A, Choudry S, Rocki K, Baydin A.G, Prunkl C, Paige B, Isayev O, **Peterson EJ**, McMahon PL, Macke J, Cranmer K, Zhang J, Wainwright H, Hanuka A, Veloso M, Assefa S, Zheng S, Pfeffer A, Simulation Intelligence: Towards a New Generation of Scientific Methods, *arXiv* 2112.03235 (2021).
- Peterson EJ, What can astrocytes compute?, bioRxiv 465192v1 (2021).
- **Peterson EJ** & Voytek B, Costs and benefits of using rhythmic rate codes, *bioRxiv* 441276v2 (2021).
- Thomas Donoghue[1], Matar Haller[1], **Erik Peterson**[1], Paroma Varma, Priyadarshini Sebastian, Richard Gao, Torben Noto, Robert T. Knight, Avgusta Shestyuk, Bradley Voytek, Parameterizing neural power spectra into periodic and aperiodic components, *Nature Neuroscience* 23 1655-1665 (2020). [1]: Co-first.
- Peterson EJ & Verstynen TD, Curiosity eliminates the exploration-exploitation dilemma, bioRxiv 671362v10 (2020).
- **Peterson EJ** & Voytek B, Homeostatic mechanisms may shape the type and duration of oscillatory modulation, *J Neurophys* 124(1) (2020).
- Izhikevich L, Gao R, **Peterson EJ** & Bradley Voytek, Measuring the average power of neural oscillations, bioRxiv 441626 (2018). Under review at J. Neurosci. Methods.
- Peterson EJ, Müyesser NA, Verstynen T & Dunovan K, Combining imagination and heuristics to learn strategies that generalize, *Neurons, Behavior, Data analysis, and Theory* 3(4) (2020).
- Agarwal A, Kumar AV, Dunovan K, **Peterson EJ**, Verstynen T & Sycara K, Better safe than sorry: evidence accumulation allows for safe reinforcement learning, *ArXiv* 1809.09147 (2018).
- **Peterson EJ** & Voytek B, Healthy oscillatory coordination is bounded by single-unit computation, *bioRxiv* 309427 (2018).
- **Peterson EJ** & Voytek B, Alpha rhythmically alters gain by modulating excitatory-inhibitory background activity, *bioRxiv* 185074v2 (2017).
- Gao RD, **Peterson EJ**, Voytek B, Inferring synaptic excitation/inhibition balance from field potentials, *Neuroimage* 158 (2017).
- **Peterson EJ**, Burke QR, Campbell AM, Belger A, Voytek B, 1/f neural noise is a better predictor of schizophrenia than neural oscillations, bioRxiv 113449v4 (2017)
- Cole SR, **Peterson EJ**, van der Meij R, Hemptinne C, Starr PA, & Voytek B, Nonsinusoidal oscillations underlie pathological phase-amplitude coupling in the motor cortex in Parkinson's disease, *J Neurosci* 37(18) (2017)
- **Peterson EJ** and Voytek B, Balanced oscillatory coupling improves information flow, *bioRxiv* 030304v2 (2016).
- **Peterson EJ** and Seger CA, In model-based fMRI significant is less than specific., *bioRxiv* 429621 (2017).
- Peterson EJ, Seger CA and Anderson CA, Many Hats: Changes in the Striatal Bold Signal Across Stimulus, Preparation, Response and Feedback, *Journal of Neurophysiology* 110(7) 1689-1702 (2013).

- Seger CA and **Peterson EJ**, Categorization = Decision Making Generalization, *Neurosci Biobehav Rev* 37(7) 1187-1200 (2013).
- Seger CA, Dennison CM, Lopez-Paniagua DL, **Peterson EJ**, and Roark AA, Dissociating Hippocampal and Basal Ganglia Contributions to Category Learning Using Stimulus Novelty and Subjective Judgments, *Neuroimage* 55(4), 1739-53 (2011).
- Seger CA, Peterson EJ, Cincotta C, Lopez-Paniagua DL and Anderson C, Dissociating the Contributions of Independent Corticostriatal Systems to Visual Categorization Learning Through the Use of Reinforcement Learning Modeling and Granger Causality Modeling, NeuroImage 50(2) 644-656 (2010).
- Bedoukian MA, Whitesell J, Peterson EJ, Clay C and Partin KM, The Stargazin C Terminus Encodes an Intrinsic and Transferable Membrane Sorting Signal, J. Biol. Chem., 283(3), 1597-1600 (2008).
- Johansson HE, Johansson MK, Wong AC, Armstrong ES, **Peterson EJ**, Grant RE, Roy MA, Reddington MV and Cook RM, BTI1, an Azoreductase with pH Dependent Substrate Specificity, *Appl Environ Microbiol* 77(12) 4223-5 (2012).
- Cheung CL, Rubinstein AI, Peterson EJ, Chatterji A, Sabirianov RF, Mei W, Lin T, Johnson JE and DeYoreo JJ, Steric and Electrostatic Complementarity in the Assembly of Two-Dimensional Virus Arrays, Langmuir 26(5) 3498–3505 (2010).

In prep

• **Peterson EJ** & Voytek B, Learning with discrete representations using continuous chaotic neural populations *In prep* (2020).

Posters

- **Peterson EJ** & Verstynen T, A way around the exploration-exploitation dilemma, presented at Conference on Cognitive Computational Neuroscience (CCN), Berlin Germany, 2019.
- **Peterson EJ** & Verstynen T, Artificial astrocyte networks, presented at The Bernstien Conference, Berlin Germany, 2019.
- Peterson EJ & Voytek B, Homeostasis and oscillatory modulation, presented at Society for Neuroscience (SFN), San Diego CA, 2018.
- Peterson EJ, Müyesser NA, Dunovan K & Verstynen T, Combining heuristics with counterfactual play in reinforcement learning, presented at Conference on Cognitive Computational Neuroscience (CCN), Philadelphia PA, 2018
- **Peterson EJ** & Voytek B, The tradeoff between oscillatory coordination and neural computation, presented at Society for Neuroscience (SFN), Washington DC, 2017.
- Peterson EJ & Voytek B, Gain control across cortical layers can be mediated by balanced oscillatory coupling, presented at Society for Neuroscience (SFN), San Diego, CA 2016.
- Haxby S & **Peterson EJ**, Learning with discrete representations using continuous chaotic neural populations, presented at Society for Neuroscience (SFN), San Diego, CA 2016.
- Gao R, Peterson EJ, & Voytek V, Spiking correlates and temporal variability of oscillatory frequency modulation, presented at Society for Neuroscience (SFN), San Diego, CA 2016.
- Rosen BQ, Peterson EJ, Campbell AM, Belger A & Voytek B, Spectral 1/f noise differences
 account for apparent oscillatory band-specific effects in Schizophrenia, presented at Society for
 Neuroscience (SFN), San Diego, CA 2016.
- L. Izhikevich L, **Peterson EJ** and Voytek B, Neural oscillatory power is not Gaussian distributed across time, presented at Society for Neuroscience (SFN), San Diego, CA 2016.
- **Peterson EJ** & Wheeler MW, The diversity of distributed decisions, presented at Society for Neuroscience (SFN), San Diego, CA 2015.

- Peterson EJ & Voytek B. Spike-field coupling does not imply spike-spike coupling, presented at Society for Neuroscience (SFN), San Diego, CA 2015.
- Noto T, Gao R, **Peterson EJ**, Voytek B. Neural network properties can be inferred from electrophysiological power spectral geometry, presented at Society for Neuroscience (SFN), San Diego, CA 2015.
- Cole SR, Peterson EJ, de Hemptinne C, Starr PA, Voytek B. Deep brain stimulation increases
 motor cortical 1/f noise and decouples high gamma amplitude from beta phase, presented at
 Society for Neuroscience (SFN), San Diego, CA 2015.
- **Peterson EJ** & Seger CS, A precise problem in model-based fMRI?, presented at Cognitive Neuroscience Society Meeting (CNS), San Francisco, CA, May 2013.
- Peterson EJ & Seger CS, Evidence for generalizable reward representations in the basal ganglia examined using fMRI and reinforcement learning, International Meeting of the Basal Ganglia Society 11, Eilat, Israel, March 2013.
- Peterson EJ & Wheeler M, Looking everywhere for the right model of perceptual decision making, Computational Neuroscience Poster Session, Center for the Neural Basis of Cognition, Pittsburgh, PA, January 2013.
- Peterson EJ & Seger CA, Many Hats: Using fMRI to Characterize the Roles and Reward Sensitivity of the Striatum Across Stimulus, Response and Feedback., International Meeting of the Basal Ganglia Society 10, Long Branch, NJ, 2010.
- Peterson EJ and Seger, CA, Reward-level dependent activity proceeding and following response selection: an fMRI study, presented at SFN2009, Chicago, IL, Fall 2009.
- Peterson EJ and Seger, CA, To Do the Right Thing: Temporal Difference Learning As Tool to Dissect the Role of Feedback in the Striatum, presented at Cognitive Neuroscience Society Meeting (CNS), San Francisco, CA, May 2007.
- Wong MK, Armstrong ES, **Peterson EJ**, Grant RE, Cook RM, and Johnanssen HJ, The BIT1 Azoredustase Colormatric and Fluormetric Reporter System, presented at Experimental Biology 2009, New Orleans, April 2009.
- Sowers BA, **Peterson EJ**, Grant RE, Lin WY, Dick DJ and Cook RM, Optimization of Probe Performance in Real-Time PCR through an Understanding of Synthesis Impurities, presented at Quantitative PCR, San Diego (CA) March, 2005.
- Peterson EJ, Weeks BL, De Yoreo JJ, and Schwartz PV, Effect of Environmental Conditions on Dip Pen Nanolithography of Mercaptohexadecanoic Acid, J. Phys. Chem B (2004), 108 (39), pp15206-15210.

Theses

- EJ. Peterson, Rewards are Categories?, PhD Dissertation (2012).
- - 2020: Toyota Research Institute: Artificial curiosity to inspire real-life learning. PI: E. Peterson. \$110,000
- Spring 2021: Instructor/Course designer for Biologically Intelligent Exploration (85-435 & 85-735) at Carnegie Mellon.
- Fall 2018: Guest lecture in Neural and Cognitive Models of Adaptive Decisions (85-435 & 85-735) at Carnegie Mellon.
- Fall 2014 2017: Multiple guest lectures in Introduction to Data Science (COGS 9) at U.C. San Diego.
- Fall 2014 2017: Multiple guest lectures in Data Science In Practice (COGS 108) at U.C. San Diego.

4

Teaching

Grants

- Fall 2012: Taught upper-division laboratory, Sense and Perception (PSY 457) at Colorado State University.
- Spring 2011: Taught upper-division laboratory, Neuroanatomy (PSY 459) at Colorado State University.

Talks

- Artificial astrocyte networks, SFN (Nanosymposium), Chicago, Oct 2019.
- Build your own brainwaves, Nerd Nite, Los Angeles, Feb 2018.
- Conflicted data science, Open San Diego, San Diego, Feb, 2016.
- The electronic dance club brain, Nerd Nite, San Diego, Oct 2016.
- In theory you're paying attention, Ignite, San Diego, Nov 2016.
- Science ambassador, Science Hack Day, San Francisco, Oct, 2014.

Press

 Brain's 'Background Noise' May Hold Clues to Persistent Mysteries, Quanta Magazine, 2021 https://www.quantamagazine.org/brains-background-noise-may-hold-clues-to-persistent-mysteries-20210208/

ACTIVITIES

- Summer 2014: Summer school in Theoretical Neuroscience, University of Waterloo.
- Summer 2003: Undergraduate Summer Research Fellowship, Lawrence Livermore National, Laboratory Livermore CA.

AWARDS

• 2010: Editor's Choice Award, Systems Neuroscience Section, NeuroImage.